Society for Linguistic Anthropology Records 1982-1986 Mss.Ms.Coll.50
American Philosophical Society
Society for Linguistic Anthropology Records
1982-1986
Mss.Ms.Coll.50
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet
In 1983, the Society for Linguistic Anthropology was formed as a section of the AAA with the goal of advancing the "study of language in its social and cultural context and to encourage communication of the results of such study." It has published the Journal of Linguistic Anthropology semiannually since 1991, and since 2001 they have given out the Edward Sapir Prize for the book making the most significant contribution to the understanding of language in society. The Society's records consist of 0.5 linear feet of administrative correspondence, newsletters, and minutes of the executive committee, 1983-1986, representing the formation and earliest years of the Society. The files are arranged chronologically, and then alphabetically.
Society for Linguistic Anthropology
Related Archival Materials note
The APS also houses the papers of Dell Hymes (Ms. Coll. 55), one of the key figures responsible for organizing the SLA.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of the Society for Linguistic Anthropology through Jane H. Hill, 1986.
Scope and Contents note
The Records of the Society for Linguistic Anthropology consist of 0.5 linear feet of administrative correspondence, newsletters, and minutes of the executive committee, representing the formation and earliest years of the Society. The files are arranged chronologically, and then alphabetically.
Biographical/Historical note
During a major reorganization of the American Anthropological Association in 1982, the president of the organization, Dell Hymes, noted that although there were relatively few specialists in linguistic anthropology, the discipline was so central to anthropology that the field should be represented on the Board of Directors, and he argued further that a section devoted to linguistic anthropology would be highly valuable. With the assistance of Victor Golla and Bill Leap, among others, an organizational meeting was held at the annual meeting of the AAA in 1982, that attracted over 100 participants and that resulted in the appointment of an organizing committee for the new society.
In 1983, the Society for Linguistic Anthropology was formed as a section of the AAA with the goal of advancing the "study of language in its social and cultural context and to encourage communication of the results of such study." The first officers included Marianne Mithun (president) and Jane H. Hill (Secretary-Treasurer), both of whom had been instrumental figures in the organizing committee. The SLA has published the Journal of Linguistic Anthropology semiannually since 1991, and since 2001 they have given out the Edward Sapir Prize for the book making the most significant contribution to the understanding of language in society.
American Anthropological Association.; Hill, Jane H.; Hymes, Dell H.; Mithun, Marianne; Anthropological linguistics--Societies, etc.; Anthropology--Societies, etc.; Linguistics--Societies, etc.
- Society for Linguistic Anthropology Records, 1982-1986; 0.5 linear feet (Box 1)
  - Founding materials, 1982-1983; 40 items
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes correspondence with Jane Hill, Dell Hymes, Marianne Mithun, et al., on formation of the organization, minutes of the Ad Hoc Committee to form the Society, draft by-laws.
  - Annual meeting, 1983; 1 item
  - Membership #1, 1983; ca.60 items
  - Membership #2, 1983; ca.60 items
  - Newsletter, 1983; 5 items
    Includes copies and drafts.
  - Annual meeting, 1984; 11 items
    Includes Executive Committee minutes.
  - General correspondence, 1984; 8 items
  - Membership, 1984; 24 items
  - Newsletter, 1984; 1 item
  - Sapir Centenary, 1984; ca.50 items
    Includes abstracts and proposals for commemorative session.
  - Annual meeting #1, 1985; 21 items
  - Annual meeting #2, 1985; 9 items
  - Elections, 1985; 18 items
  - Membership, 1985; 2 items
  - Newsletter, 1985; 16 items
  - Annual meeting #1, 1986; 21 items
  - Annual meeting #2, 1986; 12 items
  - Elections, 1986; 23 items
  - Membership, 1986; 5 items
  - Newsletter, 1986; 25 items